<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on a French Testament printed at Bordeaux, an. Dom. MDCLXXXVI pretended to be translated out of the Latin into French by the divines of Louvain / by Richard Kidder ...</title>
            <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12105240</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12105240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1013:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on a French Testament printed at Bordeaux, an. Dom. MDCLXXXVI pretended to be translated out of the Latin into French by the divines of Louvain / by Richard Kidder ...</title>
                  <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Criticism, Textual.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54146:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON A <hi>French Teſtament</hi> PRINTED AT BORDEAUX, An. Dom. MDCLXXXVI.</p>
            <p>Pretended to be Tranſlated out of the <hi>LA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIN</hi> into <hi>FRENCH</hi> By the Divines of <hi>LO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>VAIN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD KIDDER,</hi> D. D. and Dean of <hi>PETERBORO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhop's Head in <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54146:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54146:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THAT the People have a right to read the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures cannot be doubted of by him that conſiders that matter with due Application, and without Prejudice. And that Man who reads theſe Holy Books with great Humility and Care, and an earneſt deſire to become better, will receive unſpeakable Advantages by it. The Governours and Paſtors of the Church are therefore obliged to promote this holy Diſpoſition, and to furniſh and aſſiſt the People, who cannot read theſe Books in their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Languages, with ſuch a true Tranſlation, and ſuch needful Explications as may render it more profitable to them.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does not abſolutely deny the People this liberty, but reſtrains it: For they have their Verſions of the Bible in the ſeveral Popiſh Countries in the Language of them. But for all that, certain it is, that many of that Church do not only diſparage theſe holy Books, but diſcourage the reading of them.</p>
            <p>And that Church, inſtead of aſſiſting the devout People in their profitable reading the Holy Scriptures, and furniſhing them with all due means to this purpoſe, hath dealt very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerely in the whole matter.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> By obtruding the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> as that Authentick Copy of the Bible, from which, in publick diſputes and queſtions, there is no appeal to be allowed, which the <hi>Trent-Council</hi> does. The Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> I grant, is venerable for its Antiquity, and is of great uſe in the Church; And is
<pb facs="tcp:54146:3"/>not always to be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpiſed or declaimed againſt, where at firſt ſight it does not ſeem perfectly agreeable to the Original Text; both becauſe it ſometime gives the true ſenſe, where it ſeems in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tter to differ; and alſo becauſe (in the N. T. eſpecially) where it differs from the preſent reading, it do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not differ from ſome ancient Copies. But yet after all it cannot always be defended: And it were not hard to give proofs of this beyond all exception whatſoever. This would be too great a digreſſion in this place: And therefore I ſhall only add (as a competent proof of it at preſent) that the moſt ſamed and allowed Commentators and Interpreters of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, do think fit very frequently to forſake the <hi>Vulgar:</hi> which I ſhall at any time make good againſt that Church whenever I ſhall be required to do it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> By commending that for the Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> which in truth is not ſo. After the above named De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the <hi>Trent-Council,</hi> the minds of men were in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence and doubtful, becauſe they knew not what Copy of the <hi>V. Latin</hi> to follow. And the Pope did not, for above twenty years after, declare what certain Copy ſhould be taken for the Authentick <hi>V. Latin.</hi> Afterwards indeed Pope <hi>Sixtus V.</hi> gave notice to the Chriſtian World what his mind was in this matter, <hi>A. D. MDLXXXIX.</hi> He puts out a Latin Bible, in the Preface whereunto he acquaints the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as follows: <q>That agreeably to the aforeſaid Decree of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> He, having called upon God, and relying upon S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Authority, for the publick good of the Church, had not thought much to ſet forth that Bible. He ſets forth his <hi>labour</hi> in chuſing the beſt readings; his <hi>deſign,</hi> that according to the Decree of the <hi>Trent Council</hi> the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Bible might be printed moſt Correct; and his <hi>performance,</hi> viz. That he had accurately purged this Edition from various Errors, and with utmoſt diligence reſtored it <hi>in priſtinam veritatem,</hi> i.e. <hi>to its ancient ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> After this declares his <hi>will,</hi> viz. He decrees that that
<pb facs="tcp:54146:3"/>Edition ſhould be taken for that <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> which the <hi>Trent Council</hi> declared Authentick. And this He tells us he does <hi>ex certâ noſtrâ ſcientiâ, deque Apoſtolicae po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatis plenitudine;</hi> i.e. <hi>from his own certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and plenitude of Apoſtolick Authority.</hi> And that it ought to be received as ſuch, <hi>ſine ulla dubitatione aut controverſiâ,</hi> i.e. <hi>without any doubt or contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</hi>
               </q> After this <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>VIII.</hi> puts out his Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and requires expreſly that that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived alſo. And this he does <hi>A. D. MDXCII.</hi> The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between that of <hi>Sixtus V.</hi> and <hi>Clement VIII.</hi> are too many to be here related. Where'tis in <hi>Clement</hi>'s Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>eduxiſtis,</hi> 'tis in that of <hi>Sixtus V. induxiſtis, Exod. xvi. 3.</hi> Where the one hath <hi>oppoſuit,</hi> 'tis <hi>appoſuit</hi> in the other, <hi>Deut. xxiv. 6. Clement</hi> hath <hi>extrinſecùs</hi> where <hi>Sixtus</hi> reads it <hi>intrinſecùs, 1 Kings vii. 8.</hi> Where <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath it <hi>à portá, Sixtus</hi> hath it <hi>ad portam, 2 Ezr. c. iii.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi> One reads <hi>latitudinem</hi> when the other reads <hi>altitudinem, Judith i. 1, 2.</hi> What in <hi>Sixtus</hi> is <hi>inſipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> is <hi>ſapientia</hi> in <hi>Clement, Ecclus. xxi. 15. Non reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> in <hi>Sixtus,</hi> is <hi>reſpicis</hi> in <hi>Clement, Hab. 1.13.</hi> Where <hi>Sixtus</hi> hath <hi>Credentes, Clement</hi> hath <hi>non Credentes, Joh. vi. 65.</hi> Where <hi>Sixtus</hi> hath <hi>interpretabilis, Clement</hi> hath <hi>in interpretabilis, Heb. v. 11.</hi> And where one hath <hi>doctas,</hi> the other hath <hi>indoctas, 2 Pet. i. 16.</hi> Yet are both theſe to be received by the authority of Pope and Council, tho' they contradict each other. And we ſhall ſtill be at the pleaſure of a Pope to give us another Authentick Copy.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath done very inſincerely in allowing Verſions which pretend to be true Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> when they are not. I ſhall more eſpecially conſider thoſe which were done into French; there was a French Bible printed at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> by the permiſſion of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>V. A. D. MDXXX.</hi> and reprinted, <hi>A. D. MDXXXIV.</hi> which differs from the preſent <hi>Vulgar.</hi> But this being done
<pb facs="tcp:54146:4"/>before the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Sixtus V.</hi> I inſiſt not upon it. After this there was another Verſion of the <hi>V. Latin</hi> into French by the care of certain <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, deputed to this purpoſe: An Edition of which, Printed at <hi>Lyons,</hi> I fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently refer to in the following Reflections. This was a Verſion of great fame and authority in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the Teſtament of <hi>Bordeaux</hi> pretends to be done by theſe Divines. So it was, that tho' this <hi>Louvain</hi> French Bible were deſigned to keep the people from reading the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Editions, yet it was complained of by ſeveral of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as Father <hi>Simon</hi> relates) as coming too near the Sentiments of the Proteſtants. It will appear (by the following Reflections) that this Verſion does not exactly agree with the preſent <hi>Vulgar.</hi> Since that have been many Popiſh Verſions in the French Tongue, which pretend to be Verſions of the Latin into French, of the N. Teſtament, in which I am particularly concerned at preſent. I ſhall mention none but ſuch as I have peruſed. The firſt is that of <hi>Amelote,</hi> who was choſen by the French Clergy to this employment, <hi>A.D.MDCLV.</hi> He hath Printed his Verſion both with and without Notes. The firſt, <hi>A.D.MDCLXVI.</hi> That without Notes I have ſeen Printed <hi>A.D.MDCLXXXVI.</hi> This was Printed with the atteſtation and approbation of ſeveral Prelates of <hi>France,</hi> with the permiſſion of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Crit. Hiſt. de Verſ. N. T.</note> and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Order. Father <hi>Simon</hi> ſays, that he was the firſt Catholick Writer that applyed himſelf with Care to turn the N. Teſtament into French. I will not deny him to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of diligence and good fame; but yet neither is this a ſtrict Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second is the Verſion Printed at <hi>Mons.</hi> This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among us, and hath been often Printed, and is of great fame, and upon many accounts a very valuable Book. But neither is this a ſtrict Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> as I could eaſily ſhew by very many inſtances, were it convenient in this place to do it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54146:4"/>
            <p>The Third is this Teſtament Printed at <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> which the following Reflections relate unto. It bears the Title of, <hi>Le Novveau Teſtament de nôtre Seigneur Jeſus Chriſt Traduit de Latin en François, par les Theologiens de</hi> Louvain, i. e. <hi>The New Teſtament of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt Tranſlated out of</hi> Latin <hi>into</hi> French, <hi>by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of</hi> Louvain. It was Printed at <hi>Bordeaux, A.D.MDCLXXXVI.</hi> It hath the approbation of two Doctors, viz. <hi>Lopes</hi> and <hi>Germain,</hi> as very profitable to thoſe who ſhall be permitted and have capacity to read it. It hath alſo the permiſſion of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bordeaux,</hi> and 'tis in that permiſſion affirmed to be <hi>reviewed</hi> and <hi>exactly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall make it appear that this is no true Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> that it is not the work of the <hi>Louvain</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines as it pretends to be: That is agrees neither with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> nor the celebrated <hi>Verſions</hi> of it which are allowed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: That is hath a conſiderable number of downright forgeries and falſifications, a great number of groſs errors, and miſtakes: That is adds to the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and takes from it: That 'tis inconſiſtent with it ſelf, and by no means corrected as to the Typographical <hi>Errata.</hi> In a word, it hath not the authority of ancient Copies or various Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to ſupport it: I dare challenge all mankind to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preface to the Rhem. Teſtam.</note>Thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have inveighed againſt the Proteſtants Verſions. They have pretended that we have no Bible. They have ſcoffed and derided us on this account. They have boaſted that they have been the faithful preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of theſe Divine Oracles, and that what we have of them we may thank them for.</p>
            <p>But lo here a proof of their inſincerity; here's that which may convince any honeſt man, even of their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that is willing to know the truth in this moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant matter. And if any ſuch ſhould read theſe Papers, I
<pb facs="tcp:54146:5"/>muſt conjure him, as he loves his Soul, to take care how he truſts that Church with the Salvation of his Soul that dares falſifie at this high rate. No man will in other caſes truſt a cheat or forger of Teſtaments and Deeds. But how great muſt this wickedneſs be then, when the Holy Oracles of God are corrupted to ſerve a turn. They that can do this can make no boggle at the moſt horrid and execrable Crimes.</p>
            <p>I did intend in the laſt Reign to have made, and to have publiſhed theſe Reflections. But I could by no means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this Teſtament either here or beyond the Seas. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that I began to ſuſpect that either there was no ſuch Book, or that it had not thoſe faults in it as had been given out. But, after I had, by means of a very learned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon, procured a Copy, I found it to be, as I have in the following Reflections truly repreſented it to the Reader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Z. Iſham, R. P. D. Henrico Epiſc. Lond. à Sacris.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob. 18. 1690.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54146:5"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON THE <hi>French New Teſtament,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>I Will not undertake to repreſent all the faults of this Tranſlation: It ſhall ſuffice to take notice of the moſt notorious, and greater number of them.</p>
            <p>I will begin with ſuch as are notorious in an high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and deſerve no better a name than <hi>falſifications</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> merely to ſerve a turn, and ſupport a Doctrine that needs confirmation. The <hi>Maſs,</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of it, ſufficiently need better proofs than have hitherto been produced. Theſe Tranſlators, in the Contents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Matth. xxvi. v.</hi> 26. tell the Reader that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did there <hi>Inſtitute the Maſs.</hi> And this <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Maſs</hi> they mention again in the Contents before <hi>Mark xiv.</hi> And they expreſly mention <hi>the Sacrifice of the Maſs</hi> in the Contents before <hi>Act. xiii.</hi> And what we tender (<hi>v.</hi> 2.) <hi>As they miniſtred to the Lord,</hi> they render by, <hi>Or comme ils offroyent an Seigneur le Sacrifice de la Meſſe,</hi> i. e. <hi>as they offered unto the Lord the Sacrifice of the Maſs.</hi> 'Tis certain that our Engliſh Verſion of that place fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> and their <hi>Rhemiſt</hi> Teſtament agrees with it herein; and <hi>Amelote</hi> renders it, <hi>lors qu'ils eſtoyent occupez au Service de Dieu,</hi> i. e. <hi>when they were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polyed in the Service of God.</hi> And the old <hi>Louvain</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thus, <hi>Eux donc ſervans en leur Miniſtere an Seigneur,</hi> i. e. <hi>as they were ſerving in their Miniſtery to the Lord.</hi> But theſe men make no ſcruple to forſake the <hi>Vulgar</hi> it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54146:6"/>ſelf, when it will not ſerve their purpoſe. I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſhewed, that <hi>Act. xiii.</hi> 2. contains no proof of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> doctrine of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of the <hi>Maſs;</hi> and do not intend to enter upon that diſpute here. 'Tis enough to obſerve that theſe Tranſlators forſake that <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> (which their Church commends and approves) when in the mean time they pretend to give us a Verſion of it.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of Purgatory as 'tis taught in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church muſt be defended: And tho' the Scripture have nothing in it to that purpoſe, yet they'll rather add to the Text, and falſifie that, than want a colour for their Doctrine. And indeed they have done it: where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us of him that ſhall be ſaved <hi>as by fire</hi> (1 Cor. iii. 15.) they have it, <hi>par le feu du Purgatoire,</hi> i.e. <hi>by the fire of Purgatory;</hi> without any diſtinction of letters at all; as if <hi>Purgatory</hi> had been in the Text as well as <hi>fire.</hi> And yet the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> (of which this is pretended to be a Tranſlation) hath only <hi>per ignem,</hi> i.e. <hi>by fire,</hi> as 'tis in our <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and ſo 'tis in the Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes.</hi> Nor is there any mention of Purgatory in the old <hi>Louvain Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> in that of <hi>Amelote,</hi> or <hi>Mons.</hi> But theſe men are hardy, and to ſupport their Doctrine will add to the Text. The <hi>Roman</hi> Church will have Marriage to be a Sacrament. Theſe Tranſlators will help her out in the defence of this Doctrine, and will rather corrupt the Text than renounce that Doctrine. And therefore (1 Cor. vii. 10.) <hi>The married</hi> is rendred by <hi>Ceux qui ſont conjoints par le Sacrement de marriage,</hi> i.e. <hi>They that are joined together by the Sacrament of marriage.</hi> But this is forgery, and a groſs addition to the Text, not only to the <hi>Greek,</hi> but to the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> alſo; and yet theſe men pretend to give us a Tranſlation of it. Again, they purſue this unexcuſable error. <hi>Be ye not unequally yoked,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle: They render it, <hi>ne vous joignez point par Sacrement de marriage,</hi> i.e. <hi>join not your ſelves by the Sacrament of marriage,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor. vi.</hi> 14. See alſo this Tranſlation of 1 <hi>Tim. iv.</hi> 3.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54146:6"/>
            <p>The Doctrine of Merits is not favoured by the Holy Scriptures. But theſe Tranſlators have preſſed them in that cauſe. <hi>That ye may be counted worthy,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Paul,</hi> (1 <hi>Theſſ. i.</hi> 5.) To the ſame ſenſe their <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it, <hi>ut digni habeamini, that you may be counted worthy.</hi> So the <hi>Rhemes</hi> Teſtament: here's a great agreement. But tho' this be the ſenſe of the <hi>Greek,</hi> their <hi>Vulgar,</hi> their <hi>Rhemiſt,</hi> yet this is too flat for theſe Tranſlators. They will have S. <hi>Paul</hi> bear witneſs to their doctrine of Merits: And therefore they render it, <hi>Aſin que-vous meritiez, &amp;c.</hi> i.e. <hi>To the end ye may merit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Thus when we are told that God <hi>is well-pleaſed</hi> with good works, <hi>Heb. xiii.</hi> 16. they will have it, <hi>on merite envers Dieu,</hi> that by them a <hi>man merits with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Church boaſts her ſelf as the only Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lick Church, and pillar of Truth. The Holy Scriptures (as well as all ancient Creeds) are ſilent in this matter. But theſe Tranſlators have by manifeſt forgery wreſted them to teſtifie in behalf of this matter. <hi>In the latter times</hi> (ſays S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>ſome ſhall depart from the faith,</hi> 1 Tim. iv. 1. <hi>de la foy Romain,</hi> i. e. <hi>from the Roman faith,</hi> ſay the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of this Tranſlation: And yet the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> the <hi>Rhemes</hi> Teſtament, that of <hi>Mons</hi> agree with our <hi>Engliſh:</hi> And as this is the ſenſe of the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the Verſions, ſo 'tis manifeſt that the addition of <hi>Roman</hi> is nothing leſs than forgery and falſification of the Text; a crime ſo great that I want words to expreſs it by. They have ſo ordered the matter that the Apoſtles words, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to us the groſs defection of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and give us warning of their dangerous errors, are made to ſpeak a quite contrary ſenſe. This appears from the words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> laſt mentioned; and will farther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from their tranſlation of the following words of the Apoſtle. What we render <hi>the doctrines of Devils,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably to both their <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> and Teſtament of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54146:7"/>
               <hi>Rhemes,</hi> they have rendred by <hi>doctrines enſignées par des diables,</hi> i.e. <hi>doctrines taught by the devils;</hi> by which they have endeavoured to divert the thoughts of the Reader from that worſhip of <hi>Damons,</hi> which ſo viſibly obtains in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. And whereas the Apoſtle goes on to deſcribe the nature of the Apoſtacy, againſt which he warns his reader (<hi>v.</hi> 3.) they have quite perverted his ſenſe, and moſt diſhoneſtly foiſted in a ſenſe that is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to the errors of their Church. <hi>Forbidding to marry,</hi> and commanding <hi>to abſtain from meats,</hi> they tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate by, <hi>condamnans le Sacrement de marriage, l'abſtinence des alimens, &amp;c.</hi> i.e. <hi>condemning the Sacrament of marriage, the abſtinence of meats, &amp;c.</hi> And thus they turn the Apoſtles words upon the <hi>reformed,</hi> as if they were the Apoſtates which the Apoſtle points at, becauſe they deny <hi>marriage</hi> to be a Sacrament, and do not think we are now obliged by that difference of meats introduced by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. In this they deal very inſincerely. And that they do ſo will appear to any indifferent perſon whatſoever. What we render <hi>forbidding to marry</hi> is not only agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Greek</hi> text, but alſo to the Verſions received in the Church of <hi>Rome, viz.</hi> that of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> the old <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain,</hi> and that of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and <hi>Mons,</hi> and that of <hi>Amelote.</hi> Whereas their Verſion is deſtitute of all Authority whatſoever. For the following words in our Verſion, And commanding <hi>to abſtain from meats:</hi> I grant indeed that, <hi>and commanding,</hi> is not in the <hi>Greek</hi> Text, and our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters have given warning of it, by Printing thoſe words in a different character from the words of the Text: But yet I will maintain that they have given the true ſenſe of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words. For tho' the words in the <hi>Greek</hi> are Elliptical, yet our <hi>Engliſh</hi> hath ſupplied the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſis</hi> no otherwiſe than the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Verſion have done, who have expreſs'd it by <hi>qui obligeront de, &amp;c.</hi> and the old <hi>Louvain</hi> gives us the ſame ſenſe. Beſides the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54146:7"/>
               <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion juſtifies our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and (which is more than all) the following words of the Apoſtle, <hi>which God hath created to be received, &amp;c.</hi> which words make it plain enough, that they are marked out who command us to abſtain from meats, <hi>which God hath created to be received.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath advanced an opinion concerning ſins <hi>Mortal</hi> and <hi>Venial.</hi> I enter not into the diſpute. 'Tis certain that theſe Tranſlators have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to bring in the Scripture, as giving expreſs ground for this diſtinction: And tho' they could not find it there, they have found a place to foiſt it into. <hi>There is a ſin not unto death,</hi> ſays S. <hi>John</hi> 1 <hi>ep.</hi> v. 17. which words they tranſlate thus, <hi>Il y a quelque pechè que n'eſt point mortel, mais veniel,</hi> i.e. <hi>There is a ſin that is not mortal, but venial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed to conſider ſome other places, in which theſe Tranſlators ſo order the matter, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in the Readers minds ſuch an Idea of Chriſtianity, as bears conformity to the preſent Doctrines, or uſages of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>Thus when the Evangeliſt mentions the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> (<hi>Matt. ii.</hi> 4. <hi>ch. xxvii,</hi> 1, 6, 62. <hi>ch. xxviii.</hi> 11.) they render it by, <hi>Princes des Prêtres,</hi> i.e. <hi>Princes of the Prieſts.</hi> This carries a ſhew of that eminence and dignity of that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which is now to be ſeen in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But theſe men are in this the leſs blameable, becauſe they do follow the letter of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> which they pretend to tranſlate. For which reaſon the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Verſion have the ſame rendring. But then theſe latter explain theſe <hi>Princes of the Prieſts</hi> by the <hi>heads of the twenty four Sacerdotal families.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They render the word <hi>Repent</hi> (<hi>Matt. iii.</hi> 2. <hi>c. iv.</hi> 17. <hi>Luk. x.</hi> 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) by <hi>faites penitence,</hi> i.e. <hi>do penance.</hi> Where they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54146:8"/>give the Reader an occaſion of a very imperfect Idea of true Repentance; it being poſſible that men may do penance (according to the importance of that phraſe in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) and not repent.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſaid of the Parents of <hi>Jeſus</hi> that they <hi>went</hi> to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Luk. ii.</hi> 41. Theſe Tranſlators tell that they went <hi>en Pelerinage,</hi> i.e. <hi>in Pilgrimage</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out juſt ground they would inſinuate that they did what is now the practice in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But there is nothing in the <hi>Greek,</hi> or <hi>Vulgar</hi> that will juſtifie this Tranſlation. And ſeveral other Verſions uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> import no more but that they went to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and the Text tells us the occaſion of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And yet theſe Tranſlators are ſo fond of inſinuating the practice of Pilgrimages, that they do it without any colour. If S. <hi>Paul</hi> mention a <hi>brother</hi> choſen <hi>to travel with us,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor. viii.</hi> 19.) theſe Tranſlators turn thoſe words by, <hi>compagnon de nôtre Pelerinage,</hi> i.e. <hi>a companion of our Pilgrimage.</hi> And the <hi>ſtrangers</hi> in S. <hi>John</hi> (<hi>ep. iii. v.</hi> 5.) are by theſe Tranſlators turn'd <hi>les Pelerins,</hi> i.e. <hi>Pilgrims.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luk. iv. 8. <hi>Him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> Thus our <hi>Engliſh</hi> render that place agreeably to the <hi>Vulgar, illi ſoli ſervies:</hi> And <hi>verbatim</hi> as the <hi>Rhemes</hi> Teſtament hath it. Theſe Tranſlators of <hi>Louvain</hi> have to the ſame ſenſe tranſlated theſe words in a Parallel place, <hi>Matt. iv.</hi> 10. <hi>a luy ſeul tu ſerviras.</hi> But here theſe men change their ſtyle and turn the ſame words thus, <hi>ſerviras de latrie à luy ſeul,</hi> i. e. <hi>thou ſhalt ſerve him only with Latria.</hi> This is to keep up the diſtinction between the Service of <hi>doulia</hi> and <hi>latria,</hi> and preſerve the ſhifts they are put to in the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie we have with them concerning their worſhipping of Creatures. The Reader will eaſily diſcern their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity, and inconſiſtency with themſelves, as well as the danger the unwary Reader will be expoſed to by ſuch a Verſion. The words in S. <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>S. Luke,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54146:8"/>are exactly the ſame both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> the places parallel, and the ſubject matter the ſame, and there is no ſhadow of reaſon for a different Verſion. Beſides, the old <hi>Louvain</hi> (which this Verſion ought to have follow'd) turns both places by the very ſame words, and agreeably to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Vulgar, à luy ſeul tu ſerviras,</hi> i.e. <hi>him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> The Verſions of <hi>Amelote</hi> and that of <hi>Mons</hi> turn both places alike, and to the ſame ſenſe which we do. Theſe men take a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which their other Interpreters would not take, and which they themſelves in S. <hi>Matthew</hi> did not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom. xv.</hi> 16. <hi>Miniſter:</hi> The <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it ſo too. And ſo does the Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> the old <hi>Louvain, Amelote,</hi> and <hi>Mons.</hi> But theſe Tranſlators, who pretend to follow the <hi>Latin,</hi> yet keep the <hi>Greek</hi> word in their Text, <hi>viz. Leytourge;</hi> but then they add even to the Text, without difference of Character, <hi>C'eſt à dire, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificateur,</hi> i.e. <hi>that is to ſay, a Sacrificer.</hi> 'Tis eaſie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the intention of this; but to reconcile this to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon honeſty is paſt my comprehenſion.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. x.</hi> 14. <hi>Flee from Idolatry.</hi> The Teſtament of <hi>Mons</hi> turns the words to the ſame ſenſe, <hi>Fuyez l'idolatrie.</hi> This agrees exactly with the <hi>Greek;</hi> the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Tranſlation and that of <hi>Amelote</hi> agree alſo with our Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines turn the words thus: <hi>Fuyez l'adoration des Idoles,</hi> i.e. <hi>Flee from the adoration of Idols.</hi> And yet 'tis evident that a man may be guilty of Idolatry tho' he worſhip no <hi>Idol.</hi> Theſe Tranſlators are not to be excuſed in this rendring: For whatever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they may ſeem to have from the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that in other places where they have equal pretence from the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> yet they do in thoſe places render as our <hi>Engliſh doth,</hi> as may be ſeen by comparing their ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, <hi>Gal. v.</hi> 20. and 1 <hi>Cor. vi.</hi> 10. with the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:54146:9"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. xi.</hi> 2. <hi>As I delivered them.</hi> This Tranſlation is ſo unexceptionable, that it is what the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, make uſe of themſelves. Nor is there in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> any thing repugnant to it, or that does ſo much as inſinuate unwritten Traditions, much leſs favour the doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church about this matter. Thus the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders theſe and the foregoing words: <hi>Et ſicut tradidivobis, praecepta mea tenetis.</hi> But theſe Divines of <hi>Louvain</hi> knew very well that their Church wanted all the help that could be got, and therefore they render the words to the advantage of their Church. <hi>Comme je vous les ay laiſsè par tradition,</hi> i.e. <hi>as I have left them with you by Tradition.</hi> Thus when the Faith is ſaid to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints (<hi>Jude v.</hi> 3.) theſe Tranſlators lay hold of the expreſſion, and tell the Reader how the Saints came by it, <hi>viz. par Tradition,</hi> i.e. <hi>by Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Tranſlators have a great regard to the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and will make their Tranſlation ſpeak what may ſerve the intereſt of it, and its known Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and uſages. I ſhould be too long if I ſhould ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſely inſiſt upon every inſtance which might be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to this purpoſe. In favour of their doctrine of the <hi>Sacriſice</hi> of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> the word <hi>Prieſts</hi> (<hi>Rev. i.</hi> 6.) is rendred by <hi>Sacriſicateurs,</hi> i.e. <hi>Sacriſicing Prieſts.</hi> In fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of their doctrine of the ſeven Sacraments, the word <hi>Myſtery</hi> (<hi>Rev i.</hi> 20.) ſhall be turned into <hi>le Sacre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> i.e. <hi>the Sacraments:</hi> with reſpect to the dignity of their Prieſts and Veſtments, the <hi>Elders</hi> upon the <hi>Seats</hi> muſt be rendred by <hi>Prieſts</hi> upon their <hi>Thrones,</hi> and their <hi>white raiment</hi> by <hi>Aubes,</hi> i.e. <hi>Albs, Rev. iv.</hi> 4. And for the antiquity of their Proceſſions, whereas the walls of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo</hi> are ſaid to have fallen after they were <hi>encompaſſed about ſeven days, Heb. xi.</hi> 30. they have it, <hi>apres une Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>after a Proceſſion</hi> of ſeven days. The Reader may collect more to this purpoſe out of this Tranſlation of <hi>Act. iii.</hi> 1. <hi>c. x.</hi> 30.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54146:9"/>
            <p>I ſhall proceed now to ſome other places where we ſhall find notorious falſities in this Tranſlation. I ſhall lay ſome of them before the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matt. xv.</hi> 5. It is <hi>a gift by whatſoever thou mighteſt be proſited by me.</hi> It is a very odd rendring of theſe words we find in this Tranſlation; viz. <hi>Tout don qui eſt de par moy, ſera à ton profit,</hi> i.e. <hi>whatſoever gift proceedeth from me ſhall profit thee.</hi> Tho' I reckon this Tranſlation far from the ſenſe of our Saviours words, yet I ſhall not inſiſt on this as a charge againſt theſe Tranſlators, becauſe this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theirs is agreeable enough to the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which they pretend to Tranſlate: And for that reaſon I paſs by their Tranſlation of <hi>Luk. ix.</hi> 50. However I cannot but take notice, that the other Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and of the greateſt ſame in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have otherwiſe rendered theſe words; and have thought the <hi>Vulgar</hi> ſo obſcure, that they have added words to their Text, to render them more intelligible. The Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Tranſlation have done this in terms that ſeem to be agreeable to the ſenſe of the <hi>Vulgar:</hi> And <hi>Amelote,</hi> another of their famous Interpreters, hath done it in terms that are very different, and much more agreeable to the ſenſe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion. Beſides, he hath given an Explication in the Margin, which gives a ſenſe of the place very different from what this Verſion of theſe <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain</hi> Divines imports, or what the Authors of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Mons</hi> have given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh. xxi.</hi> 22. <hi>If I will,</hi> theſe Tranſlators turn in by, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veux, I will:</hi> Here the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> will not bear them out. Tho' in the preſent Copy 'tis <hi>ſic volo,</hi> yet <hi>Benedictus</hi> puts <hi>ſi</hi> in the Margin of his Edition (Printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> A. D. 1558.) in the room of <hi>ſic,</hi> and with good reaſon. This reading is agreeable to the <hi>Greek</hi> Text. The <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> allow that ſome read it ſo; the reading is confirmed by the <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion; and the Authors of the Verſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54146:10"/>of <hi>Mons,</hi> who likewiſe profeſs to give us the Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> tranſlate by, <hi>ſi je veux,</hi> that is, <hi>if I will.</hi> And the old tranſlation of <hi>Louvain</hi> does alſo agree with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> herein. Beſides, in the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> Teſtament printed by <hi>Plantin, A. D.</hi> 1574. we find <hi>ſi</hi> in the Margin, and in his Edition, <hi>A. D.</hi> 1582. of the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> Bible, the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines give the Reader notice that they find it <hi>ſi</hi> in three MSS. of the <hi>Vulgar:</hi> After all it appears from the Context that this is the true reading, as any indifferent perſon will eaſily underſtand. And in the <hi>French</hi> Bible printed at <hi>Antwerp, A. D.</hi> 1534. by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Charles</hi> V. 'tis rendred by <hi>ſy,</hi> if, as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> hath it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom. viii.</hi> 1. There is <hi>therefore now no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate thus, <hi>Il n'y a donc rien maintenant qui merite la dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation en ceux qui ſont en J. Chriſt.</hi> i. e. <hi>There is therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now that deſerves damnation in them which are in J. Chriſt.</hi> Here the <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> which thoſe men pretond to give us a Verſion of, agrees with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and does by no means favour the <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion. The ſame may be ſaid not only of the <hi>Greek,</hi> but the Verſions of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and of the old <hi>Louvain</hi> and <hi>Amelote,</hi> and <hi>Mons</hi> alſo; all of them turned from the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom. xvi.</hi> 5. <hi>Achaia.</hi> Theſe Tranſlators have it <hi>Aſia;</hi> nor do I inſiſt upon it, becauſe in this they do indeed ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. i.</hi> 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church: Al' Evang ille,</hi> i. e. <hi>To the Goſpel.</hi> This is ſo groſs that there is neither ſhadow or defence for it.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. vii.</hi> 5. <hi>Defraud you not one another.</hi> The <hi>Vulgar</hi> agrees, <hi>nolite fraudare invicem.</hi> The Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes</hi> gives the very ſame ſenſe. The old <hi>Louvain</hi> Edition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees exactly with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the Verſions of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lote</hi> and that of <hi>Mons</hi> give the ſame ſenſe with the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54146:10"/>and the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> But this of the <hi>Louvain</hi> a ſenſe that is contradictory, viz. <hi>Ne vous donnés pas le devoir l'une à l'autre.</hi> And yet is this Verſion obtruded upon the world as a Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> and the approved Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Louvain,</hi> tho' it agree with neither of them.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. xv. 5. <hi>We ſhall not all ſleep, but we ſhall all be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> Thus are theſe words tranſlated, <hi>Ileſt vray que nous reſſuſciterous tous, mais nous ne ſerous point tous changez,</hi> i. e. <hi>it is true that we ſhall all be raiſed up, but we ſhall not be all changed.</hi> The <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion confirms our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo do our ordinary <hi>Greek</hi> Copies. But ſince there is a various reading in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the <hi>Vulgar</hi> favours this <hi>French</hi> Verſion, I ſhall not inſiſt upon this place.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. xvi. 2. <hi>As</hi> God <hi>hath proſpered him. Recondens quod ei bene placuerit,</hi> V. L. <hi>Cequ'il a envie de donner.</hi> Whatever agreement may ſeem to be here between this <hi>French</hi> and the Verſion of the <hi>V. Latin,</hi> 'tis certain that both <hi>Amelote</hi> and the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſtament give us a different ſenſe of the words.</p>
            <p>2 Cor. iv. 2. <hi>We have renounced the hidden things of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſty. Abdicamus occulta dedecoris,</hi> V. L. Here's a good agreement. But theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines render it, <hi>nous retranchons ce qui eſt ſolide, qu'on eſt oblige de Cacher.</hi> But the Teſtament of <hi>Amelote,</hi> and that of <hi>Mons</hi> interpret the place in a ſenſe agreeable to our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and ſo does the old <hi>Louvain</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>2 Cor. iv. 7. <hi>By the word of truth, by the power of God. In verbo veritatis, in virtute Dei.</hi> Here the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> exactly. But nothing can be more extravagant than our <hi>French</hi> Verſion is. <hi>En chaſtetè, en connoiſſance,</hi> &amp;c. i.e. <hi>in chaſtity, in knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo that Verſion goes on with thoſe vertues mentioned (even in that Verſion as well as in the Text) the verſe before, and after all leaves out the <hi>word of truth,</hi> tho' at laſt it mention the <hi>power of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54146:11"/>
            <p>2 Cor. ix. 2. <hi>The forwardneſs of your mind.</hi> The <hi>V. Latin</hi> agrees with this Verſion of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> And the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rhemes</hi> agrees with the Latin. But theſe <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain</hi> Divines render it, <hi>la promptitùde de vótre coúrage,</hi> i. e. <hi>the forwardneſs of your courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gal. iv. 25. <hi>For this Agar is mount Sinai in Arabia, and anſwereth to Jeruſalem.</hi> Thus 'tis rendred in our <hi>French</hi> Teſtament, <hi>Car Sina eſt une montagneen Arabie, laquelle eſt conjointe à Jeruſalem,</hi> i. e. <hi>For Sinai is a mountain in Arabia, which is conjoined to Jeruſalem.</hi> It muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the <hi>V. Latin</hi> agrees hereunto. For thus the words of that Verſion are. <hi>Sina enim mons eſt in Arabia, qui conjunctus eſt ei, quae nunc eſt Jeruſalem.</hi> Where, if by <hi>conjoined,</hi> be underſtood as much as <hi>contiguous,</hi> or <hi>conter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous,</hi> 'tis certain in matter of fact, that it was not near <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 'Tis evident beſides, that this ſenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees not with the Apoſtles purpoſe: nor is it to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that the author of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Verſion could have this meaning: And therefore theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines ſhould have better conſidered this matter, and not have given the ordinary reader ſuch an occaſion of a groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. We ſind the Authors of other Verſions of the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> have been wary in this particular, well conſidering how eaſie it was to miſtake in this matter. Inſtead of <hi>qui conjunctus eſt,</hi> the Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes</hi> hath it, <hi>which hath affinity to.</hi> And the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſtament expreſſeth it by <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente la Jeruſalem</hi> i.e. Sinai <hi>repreſents</hi> Jeruſalem. And the Verſion of <hi>Amelote</hi> of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> (Printed at <hi>Paris, A. D.</hi> 1686. with large approbations of the Biſhops and Divines of the <hi>French</hi> Church) renders it thus, <hi>qui a du rapport avec la Jeruſalem.</hi> Beſides all this, the former Verſion of the Divines of <hi>Louvain,</hi> of the <hi>Latin</hi> into <hi>French,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Lyons, A. D.</hi> 1599. have thus tranſlated this paſſage: <hi>Correſpondance à la Jeruſalem,</hi> i. e. <hi>Sinai</hi> was a mountain <hi>correſponding to Jeruſalem.</hi> This agrees with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:54146:11"/>with the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac,</hi> and with the deſign of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Whereas the other <hi>French</hi> Verſion is groſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with all theſe. But the Authors of it on other occaſions, make no ſcruple of departing from the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> where there was no cauſe for it, but adhere to it when there is.</p>
            <p>Eph. v. 9. <hi>Fruit of the ſpirit. Le Fruit de la lumiere.</hi> So does this <hi>French</hi> Verſion render it, viz. <hi>the fruit of the light.</hi> I will not here charge theſe Divines, becauſe the <hi>Vulgar</hi> reads it ſo, and we find it ſo in a <hi>Greek</hi> Copy, and the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riac</hi> Verſion follows this reading. But then the Verſion of <hi>Mons</hi> puts <hi>ſpirit</hi> for <hi>light</hi> in the Margin.</p>
            <p>2 Theſſ. ii. 7. <hi>The myſtery.</hi> This Verſion of ours agrees with the <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Syriac,</hi> the <hi>Kulgar;</hi> and with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> of <hi>Mons,</hi> and of <hi>Amelote,</hi> and yet for all that our <hi>French</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath it, <hi>le decret.</hi> So that the Authors of it can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the <hi>Vulgar</hi> whenever they think ſit.</p>
            <p>Hebr. ix. 6.—<hi>The Service</hi> of God. This by our <hi>French</hi> is rendred by, <hi>les Services des Sacrifices,</hi> that is, <hi>the Services of Sacrifices.</hi> Nothing can deſend theſe Tranſlators but the <hi>Vulgar</hi> only, which renders it by <hi>ſacrificiorum officia:</hi> yet is there nothing in the <hi>Greek</hi> to this purpoſe, and the <hi>Syriac</hi> is as far from it. And we know very well that the Prieſts buſineſs in the firſt Tabernacle was the ordering the Candles, placing the Shew-bread, and burning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe. The Sacrifices were offered in the Court upon the Altar of Braſs; there the bloud of the Sacriſice was ſprinkled, and generally the body of it was there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. And the oblations offered there were <hi>Sacrifices</hi> in the moſt common ſenſe of the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> 'Tis true indeed the <hi>Vulgar</hi> does in great meaſure excuſe theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, and would more effectually do it, had they given us a ſtrict Verſion of it. But they forſake it when 'tis not for their turn, let it be never ſo juſtifiable,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54146:12"/>but keep cloſe to it (as in this place) when 'tis faulty. For that it is ſo is notorious: And this is inſinuated by ſeveral Popiſh Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which in this place vary from it. <hi>E. G.</hi> The Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion very honeſtly decline the <hi>Vulgar</hi> as abſurd in this place. What we render <hi>accompliſhing the Service of God,</hi> thus do they expreſs it, viz. <hi>qui exerpoient le Saint mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere,</hi> i.e. The Prieſts, <hi>who exerciſed the holy miniſtery.</hi> And <hi>Amelote</hi> thus, <hi>poury accomplir le Culte de Dieu,</hi> i. e. <hi>For the accompliſhing the worſhip</hi> (or Service) <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heb xi. 8. <hi>Receive:</hi> this in our <hi>Fr.</hi> tranſlation is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Concevoir</hi> without any authority, or ſhadow of it.</p>
            <p>Ver. 19. <hi>In a figure,</hi> Fr. T. <hi>pour exemple d'obeiſſance:</hi> i. e. <hi>for an example of obedience.</hi> This is a moſt groſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation of the Text: Nor will the <hi>Vulgar</hi> help out this Verſion. 'Tis true that Verſion hath it <hi>in parabolam:</hi> But this will not juſtifie our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines. The <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> indeed tranſlate it, <hi>for a parable,</hi> but they put an Explication in the Margin, <hi>viz.</hi> i.e. <hi>in figure and myſtery of Chriſt dead, and alive again.</hi> This is indeed to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines ſeem to have no ſhame left in their Verſion of the place. For they add to the Text at pleaſure, the word <hi>obedience</hi> which the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath not. <hi>Amelote</hi> renders it, <hi>comme une figure myſterieuſe,</hi> i.e. <hi>as a myſterious figure.</hi> And the Verſion of <hi>Mons, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me d'entre les morts,</hi> en figure <hi>de la reſurrection:</hi> So that in truth they render the place <hi>in a figure,</hi> juſt as our <hi>Engliſh.</hi> For the reſt of their words are but Explication, and printed in another letter. And the old <hi>Fr.</hi> Edition of the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines modeſtly render it by <hi>figure</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Heb. xi. 21 — <hi>Worſhipped</hi> leaning <hi>upon the top of his ſtaff.</hi> Fr. tranſlation, <hi>adora le bout du baſton d'iceluy,</hi> i. e. <hi>he ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the top of his ſtaff.</hi> V. L. <hi>&amp; adoravit faſtigium virgae ejus.</hi> The <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have here followed the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latin,</hi> which they frequently forſake, and are not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54146:12"/>therefore to be charged with miſ rendring that Verſion. But the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac</hi> favour not this rendring. And the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation receive it not into their Text, but put it into the Margin: and they ſo turn it as it ſpeaks only a profound inclination towards the Enſign of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s grandeur, and therein a veneration of the kingdom of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whoſe type he was; as they have explained this matter in the Margin. But our <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain</hi> Divines have not taken that care, to preſerve the ſimple people from Idolatry, either in the Verſion, or any Explication of it.</p>
            <p>Jam. iii. 7. <hi>For every kind of beaſts,</hi> &amp;c. Here the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines depart from the <hi>Vulgar</hi> without any ſhadow of reaſon. For as they leave out the word <hi>Serpents;</hi> ſo after thoſe words, <hi>hath been tamed,</hi> they put in <hi>par reptibles,</hi> i. e. <hi>by creeping things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Pet. iv. 15. <hi>A buſie body in other mens matters.</hi> French tranſlation, <hi>convoiteux des biens d'autruy,</hi> i.e. <hi>covetous of other mens goods.</hi> 'Tis true the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it <hi>appetitor alienorum;</hi> but yet there is not ſufficient cauſe from that Verſion for this rendring: For the <hi>murderer</hi> and <hi>thief</hi> named before, are <hi>alienorum appetitores,</hi> in the ſenſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for. The Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation were ſo ſenſible of this, that they tranſlate it thus, <hi>Se mêlant te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merairement de ce qui ne le regarde pas,</hi> i. e. <hi>one that raſhly meddles with that which does not belong to him.</hi> This <hi>Verſion</hi> agrees with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and with the <hi>Greek.</hi> And what we render <hi>evil-doer,</hi> in the ſame <hi>verſe,</hi> they alſo render to the ſame ſenſe agreeably to the Original <hi>Greek;</hi> tho' in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> it be now <hi>maledicus,</hi> and by the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines is rendred <hi>mediſans;</hi> it is very probable that it was in the <hi>Vulgar maleficus</hi> at firſt. In which conjecture I am the more confirmed from what I find in the note of <hi>Amelote</hi> upon the place, who does ingenuouſly conſeſs that it is highly probable that the preſent <hi>Greek</hi> is to be followed,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54146:13"/>and affirms, that there is no MS. or Interpreter that hath it otherwiſe; and that S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> read <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leficus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Joh. iv. 3. <hi>That confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh.</hi> Fr. tranſlation, <hi>qui ſepare Jeſus-Chriſt,</hi> i.e. <hi>that ſeparates Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>Rhemiſt</hi> hath it, <hi>that diſſolveth Jeſus.</hi> And all this from the <hi>Vulgar</hi> who hath it <hi>qui ſolvit Jeſum.</hi> I will not charge the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines here with miſ-tranſlating the <hi>Vulgar;</hi> I only obſerve that they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to it ſtiffly when it departs from the <hi>Greek,</hi> as it does here by the confeſſion of the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nor does it only depart from the <hi>Greek,</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſufficient ground: For whereas 'tis pretended that the <hi>Vulgar</hi> reading is grounded upon ancient Copies, and that the <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> and ſuch as divide the <hi>Divinity</hi> of Chriſt from his <hi>Humanity</hi> have corrupted the Text; a late learned Writer of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſhewed that there is not ſufficient ground for this charge. He does maintain that the preſent <hi>Greek</hi> is followed by the <hi>Oriental</hi> Verſions,<note place="margin">P. Simon Hiſt. Crit. du Text. d. N.T. p. <hi>356.</hi>
               </note> by S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and S. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> and that that of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> is not very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: and that 'tis probable it came as a Marginal Note at firſt, and afterwards crept into the Text.</p>
            <p>1 Joh. v. 1. <hi>Whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Quicónque croit que Jeſus Chriſt eſt le Chriſt.</hi> Theſe Divines of <hi>Louvain</hi> have no pretence from the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> nor (I dare affirm it) from any Verſion extant. 'Tis their own intirely: <hi>whoſoever believeth that Jeſus Chriſt is the Chriſt,</hi> is the ſenſe of their Verſion. Any man that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands common ſenſe amongſt Chriſtians muſt ſee the egregious folly of it. And theſe men do, where there is only <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Text, not only here but, <hi>v.</hi> 5. of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> add the word <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that without the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Vulgar,</hi> tho' they ſpoil the ſenſe of the place by it. I paſs by their rendring of, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 8. of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54146:13"/>
               <hi>chapter:</hi> they agree with the <hi>Latin;</hi> and I ſhould be too long if I ſhould inſiſt upon all the differences between the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and the preſent <hi>Greek;</hi> upon which conſideration alſo I paſs by their Verſion of <hi>Jude v.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Rev. v. 10, 12. <hi>Kings,</hi> v. 10. Fr. Tr. <hi>Royaumes,</hi> i.e. <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms;</hi> 'tis indeed <hi>Regnum</hi> in the <hi>V. Latin,</hi> but the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation agree with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac,</hi> and ſo does <hi>Amelote</hi> alſo: I have alſo reaſon to believe that the Copy of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> before <hi>Clement VIII.</hi> had it <hi>Reges.</hi> I find in a <hi>French</hi> Bible, printed 1534. at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> which is a Tranſlation of the then <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and was printed by order of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>V.</hi> that 'tis rendred to the ſame ſenſe with our <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This agrees with what follows alſo, <hi>viz. Prieſts,</hi> which our <hi>Fr.</hi> tranſlation (after its manner) turns into <hi>Sacrificateurs,</hi> i. e. <hi>Sacrificers.</hi> If the firſt were duly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the following might as well have been turn'd by <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> What we render <hi>riches, v.</hi> 12. the <hi>French</hi> tranſlation turns by <hi>divinitè,</hi> according to the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. xviii. 20. <hi>Holy Apoſtles. French</hi> tranſlation, <hi>Saints, Apoſtres,</hi> i.e. <hi>Saints, Apoſtles.</hi> Thus do theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines render it. And yet the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> agrees with our Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo do the Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> of <hi>Mons,</hi> of <hi>Amelote;</hi> and the old <hi>Verſion</hi> of the <hi>Louvain,</hi> printed at <hi>Lyons,</hi> and that printed at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> 1534.</p>
            <p>Matt. 1.11. <hi>About the time they were carried away to Babylon. Fr.</hi> tranſlation, <hi>quand ils furent tranſportez en Babylon,</hi> i. e. <hi>when they were tranſported in Babylon.</hi> 'Tis very certain as to the matter of fact, that it was before the tranſportation that <hi>Joſias</hi> begat his children, for he dyed before that captivity. Nor will the rendring of the <hi>Vulgar, in tranſmigratione Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonis</hi> by any means juſtifie this <hi>Fr.</hi> tranſlation. For, beſides that it does not anſwer this <hi>French</hi> Verſion, ſo it is not hard to give a ſenſe of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> that is conſiſtent with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact. Thus the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders the whole verſe, <hi>Joſias antem genuit Jechoniam, &amp; fratres ejus in tranſmigratione Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonis.</hi> Now the <hi>fratres ejus,</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>in tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54146:14"/>Babylonis,</hi> tho' the <hi>genuit</hi> cannot. The other Popiſh <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> have ſhewed greater care. That of <hi>Rhemes</hi> keeps ſtrictly to the <hi>Vulgar:</hi> that of <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Amelote</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, <hi>vers le temps, &amp;c.</hi> i.e. <hi>towards the time</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> were carried into <hi>Babylon,</hi> in which they agree with the <hi>Greek,</hi> with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and with matter of Fact.</p>
            <p>Matt. i. 25. <hi>Till ſhe had brought forth, &amp;c.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>quand elle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta,</hi> i.e. <hi>when ſhe brought forth.</hi> And yet the <hi>P. Latin</hi> hath it, <hi>donec peperit,</hi> agreeably to our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to the <hi>Greek;</hi> and the Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes</hi> is conformable to them: nor is there any reaſon we ſhould forſake this Verſion: we can defend it, as it is, both againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> and the followers of <hi>Helvidius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Matt. xix, 1. <hi>Theſe ſayings,</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Ces propos.</hi> By an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolete word, uſed indeed in the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Edition, printed <hi>A. D.</hi> 1599. But the later Interpreters have thought ſit to chuſe a word of common and preſent uſe. <hi>Amelote</hi> renders it, <hi>ſon diſcours,</hi> the <hi>Mons</hi> Verſion, <hi>ces diſcours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark iii. 29. <hi>In danger of eternal damnation.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Coupable d'un peché eternel,</hi> i.e. <hi>guilty of an eternal ſin.</hi> I do not blame our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines here, becauſe the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it <hi>reus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terni delicti.</hi> But yet there is no reaſon however to adhere to the very words of the <hi>Latin</hi> here, becauſe the ſenſe of thoſe words may be more intelligibly expreſs'd. And this <hi>Amelote</hi> hath done, who renders it by, <hi>Coupable d'un crime qui ne ſera jamais pardonne,</hi> i.e. <hi>guilty of a crime that ſhall never be forgiven.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid, as to <hi>Luk.</hi> ii. 15. where what we render <hi>this thing,</hi> theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have rendred by <hi>ce verb,</hi> i.e. <hi>this word:</hi> wherein indeed they exactly follow the letter of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and ſo far I charge them not: but then they more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the letter than the ſenſe of the place. And this the Authors of the <hi>Verſion</hi> of <hi>Mons</hi> were aware of, and therefore have only <hi>ce,</hi> and take no notice in their Text of <hi>Verbum</hi> in the <hi>Latin; Amelote</hi> does the ſame. And the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion renders it, <hi>ceſte choſe,</hi> i.e. <hi>this thing,</hi> as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> does. 'Tis well known that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies not only <hi>word</hi> but <hi>thing,</hi> and that according to the ſubject matter, to which the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Greek</hi> anſwers exactly.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54146:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Luk.</hi> vii. 3. <hi>The Elders.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>des Prêtres,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Prieſts.</hi> Theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines are ſingular in their Verſion here, and whereas they pretend to tranſlate the <hi>V. Latin,</hi> yet they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it whenever they pleaſe. For the <hi>Vulgar</hi> here agrees with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion, and renders the <hi>Greek</hi> by, <hi>Seniores;</hi> the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſtament by, <hi>Senateurs; Amelote</hi> by, <hi>Anciens;</hi> and ſo does the old <hi>Louvain;</hi> and the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> by, the <hi>Auncients.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rom. i. 4.—<hi>with power, according to the ſpirit of holineſs, by the reſurrection of the dead;</hi> which words are thus rendred by the <hi>Vulgar in virtute, ſecundùm ſpiritum ſanctificationis ex reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione mortuorum, &amp;c.</hi> This Verſion agrees well with our <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Let us ſee how our Divines of <hi>Louvain</hi> render the <hi>V. Latin.</hi> Thus they do it. <hi>Par la puiſſance qu'il a recue de faire les miracles, par l'eſprit de ſanctification des ſiens, &amp; par la reſurrection des morts,</hi> i.e. <hi>By power which he received to work miracles, by the ſpirit of ſanctification of his own, and by the reſurrection of the dead.</hi> Let any man judge if this be a true Tranſlation of the <hi>Vulgar:</hi> 'tis a Paraphraſe rather, or ſhort Comment, an addition to the Text without any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the Reader, by any different character, what is Text and what is not. This is very unfair, and does not become men of Probity and Sincerity, but rather ſpeaks great negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, or fraud: for it is to be conſider'd that theſe men add to the Text. They conſider not the variety of Particles, not only in the <hi>Greek</hi> Text, but in the verſion of the <hi>V. Latin.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the <hi>Latin, In, ſecundùm, ex,</hi> are all rendred alike by theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Par. Amelote</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was ſo careful that he renders them by three ſeveral <hi>French</hi> particles, <hi>viz. dans, ſelon,</hi> and <hi>par.</hi> The Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation do ſo alſo; ſo do the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a difference, and turn them by, <hi>in, according to, by.</hi> Our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines are not ſo nice; 'tis no matter what the <hi>Vulgar</hi> does, they'll uſe their freedom.</p>
            <p>Gal. v. 19. <hi>Laſciviouſneſs;</hi> V. I. <hi>Luxuria;</hi> Mons, <hi>la diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Amelote, <hi>la laſcivité;</hi> Rhemiſt, <hi>lecherie.</hi> But, tho' here be a conſiderable agreement in theſe Verſions, our <hi>Louvain</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines turn it by, <hi>inſolence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54146:15"/>
            <p>1 Cor. iv. 5. <hi>Praiſe.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>la lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ange qui luy eſt due,</hi> i. e. <hi>the praiſe that is due to him.</hi> Whereas there is nothing but <hi>praiſe</hi> in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> the reſt is added by the <hi>Louvain</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, without any diſtinction of character.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. xi. 10. <hi>For this cauſe ought the woman to have power on her head, becauſe of the Angels.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Partant la femone à cauſe des Anges, qui la voyent, doit avoir ſur ſa téte, un en ſeigne qu'elle eſt ſous puiſſance,</hi> i. e. <hi>Therefore the woman becauſe of the Angels, who ſee her, ought to have upon her head a mark that ſhe is in ſubjection.</hi> V. L. <hi>ideò debet mulier poteſtatem habere ſupra caput propter Angelos.</hi> The fault which I find with theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines is only this, That they do not give us the ſtrict Verſion of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which they pretend to tranſlate, but add words of their own to the text without any different character; which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> hath not done, nor ought any Interpreters to do.</p>
            <p>Eph. iv. 12. <hi>For the perfecting of the Saints.</hi> V. L. <hi>ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummationem Sanctorum.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>pour l'aſſemblage des Saints,</hi> i.e. <hi>for the coagmentation</hi> (or, joining together) <hi>of the Saints.</hi> I do not deny but that the <hi>Greek</hi> word may inſinuate ſuch a ſenſe, and I will allow that it refers to Architecture, and that it is well enough expreſs'd by this <hi>French</hi> word, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies no leſs. But theſe men pretend to turn the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and all the queſtion betwixt us is, whether or no they have done that truly. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> expreſſeth the ſenſe of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> better. And the Popiſh Verſions agree in the ſame ſenſe. The old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion renders it by, <hi>pour la conſummation des Saints.</hi> The <hi>Rhemiſts, to the conſummation of the Saints.</hi> That of <hi>Mons</hi> by, <hi>a fin qu'ils travaillent a la perfection des Saints;</hi> i.e. <hi>that they may labour for the perfection of the Saints.</hi> And <hi>Amelote</hi> thus, <hi>pour rendre les Saints perfaits,</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to our <hi>Engliſh, for the perfecting of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. ii. 17. <hi>Service.</hi> V. I. <hi>Obſequium.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>la Liturgie.</hi> I appeal to any indifferent man, whether this be a Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Latin</hi> or not. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> render it as we do, by the word <hi>Service;</hi> ſo does <hi>Amelote:</hi> and ſo it is in the old E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Louvain,</hi> printed at <hi>Lyons, A.D.</hi> 1599. and in an older
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54146:15"/>Edition of the <hi>Fr.</hi> Bible, printed at <hi>Antwerp, A.D.</hi> 1534. Theſe men retain the <hi>Greek</hi> word, and are ſo far from the regard which was due from them to the <hi>Latin,</hi> that they render it not at all. The Reader, who conſiders how they have rendred <hi>Acts</hi> xiii. 2. and knows the doctrine of that Church, will eaſily underſtand the drift of theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines in this place.</p>
            <p>Phil. iii. 2.—<hi>the conciſion.</hi> V. L. <hi>conciſionem.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>la cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciſion.</hi> Theſe men ſeem to have no regard to truth. For here not only the <hi>Greek,</hi> but their <hi>Vulgar,</hi> that of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> their old <hi>Louvain</hi> tranſlation, that of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and <hi>Amelote,</hi> are againſt them. They all agree with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but theſe Divines ſtand alone by themſelves.</p>
            <p>Col. ii. 18. <hi>Worſhipping of Angels.</hi> V. L. <hi>Religione Angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Religion donnée à Moiſe par des Anges,</hi> i. e. <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion given to Moſes by Angels.</hi> According to this account of things, the words contain only a warning againſt being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> I will by no means enter into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, but keep my ſelf to my deſign. 'Tis moſt certain that theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have not dealt ſincerely with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in pretending to tranſlate the <hi>Vulgar;</hi> when they do in truth add to it, and put their own ſenſe upon it. The <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Angels</hi> can never be proved to import the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Theſe Divines add to the Text to avoid its force againſt the practices of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Whereas the old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>Louvain</hi> keep ſtrictly to the <hi>V. Latin</hi> without any ſuch addition; ſo do the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> alſo, and the <hi>Antwerp</hi> Bible. The <hi>Syriac</hi> underſtands the place of the worſhip of <hi>Angels:</hi> and the <hi>Mons Teſtament,</hi> and <hi>Amelote</hi> alſo interpret the place of the ſuperſtitious worſhip of <hi>Angels.</hi> The latter of theſe (in his Preface to this Epiſtle) tells us of certain Philoſophers, followers of <hi>Plato,</hi> who held the Angels to be Gods, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitects of the world, and paid them particular honours, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them with certain Ceremonies, and advanced them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and feigning that they were by certain viſions engag'd to this worſhip: and that S. <hi>Paul</hi> does in this <hi>Chap.</hi> fortifie them, to whom he writes this Epiſtle, and in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54146:16"/>theſe very words of this xviii. verſe, againſt theſe illuſions, he adds, That theſe ſeem to be the <hi>Angelici</hi> mentioned by S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin;</hi> a Sect that had taken root in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and condemn'd by the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Canon xxxv. And that <hi>Theodoret</hi> affirms that this Sect had built ſeveral Oratories to S. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael;</hi> to which was oppoſed the Temple of S. <hi>Michael</hi> at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs,</hi> where God alone was adored, and the Archangel ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured as a creature.</p>
            <p>1 Tim. iii. 11. <hi>Grave.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Publiques,</hi> i.e. <hi>publick.</hi> The <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> renders it by <hi>padicas.</hi> Nothing can defend this Verſion of our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines. We may indeed ſuppoſe it an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Preſs: but there is no notice of it. And we ſhall find a great number of thoſe errors beſides.</p>
            <p>2 Tim. iv. 11. <hi>For the miniſtery.</hi> V.L. <hi>in miniſterium.</hi> The <hi>Rhemiſts, for the miniſtery.</hi> Amelote, <hi>dans le miniſtere.</hi> Mons Tr. <hi>pour le miniſtere de P Evangile.</hi> Old <hi>Louvain</hi> Tr. <hi>pour Servir.</hi> Here's agreement ſufficient, and all comes to the ſame ſenſe. But theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines render it, <hi>pour me ſervir de Diacre,</hi> i. e <hi>to ſerve me as a Deacon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heb. i. 7. <hi>Miniſters.</hi> The <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it, <hi>Miniſtros.</hi> The other Popiſh tranſlations agree with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth. That of <hi>Rhemes</hi> renders by <hi>miniſters:</hi> that of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lote</hi> hath it, <hi>miniſtres.</hi> So 'tis alſo in that of <hi>Mons,</hi> and ſo it is alſo in the old Edition of the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines. It ought to be ſo in this tranſlation of the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines. But theſe men have a turn to ſerve, they muſt juſtifie their tranſlation of <hi>Act.</hi> xiii. 2. the <hi>Greek</hi> word here muſt therefore either not be turn'd (vid. <hi>Phil.</hi> ii. 17. with our <hi>French</hi> tranſlation,) or if it be it muſt ſerve their purpoſe. And therefore, tho' againſt all reaſon, and authority whatſoever, they tranſlate it here by <hi>Sacrificateurs,</hi> i.e. <hi>Sacrificers?</hi> 'tis very certain, that there was no reaſon for their interpreting, <hi>Act.</hi> xiii. 2. as they have done, unleſs they do think that a good reaſon, which Monſieur <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> once gave,<note place="margin">Simon. Hiſt. Cris. des verſal. N.T.</note> when he was ask'd, why he turn'd that place to the ſame ſenſe; the reaſon he gave was, <hi>Becauſe he had been often demanded by the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>what Scripture mentioned that the Apoſtles ſaid maſs</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:54146:16"/>
            <p>Heb. vii. 22. <hi>a Surety.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Caution.</hi> Here theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines take a great liberty; for they depart from the <hi>V. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> which renders it <hi>ſponſor:</hi> and the <hi>Rhemiſt</hi> Interpreters of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> render it <hi>ſurety,</hi> as we have done. That is alſo the meaning of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac</hi> word: Nor does the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation, <hi>Amelote,</hi> or old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion render it by <hi>caution,</hi> as theſe men do without any reaſon or authority.</p>
            <p>Heb. ix. 10. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntil the time of reformation.</hi> Here our <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain</hi> Divines add to the Text, without any difference of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. For whereas the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it, <hi>ad tempus correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> they render it, <hi>juſques au temps que ces choſes ſoyent corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gées.</hi> A liberty this is, which the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines did not take; they keep cloſe to the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> And tho' the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Verſion add to the Text, yet they do it in a character which gives warning of it to the Reader.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now reflect upon ſome other queſtionable places, which the Tranſlators of the <hi>N. T.</hi> into <hi>French</hi> are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for; ſuch are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>Act. xii. 30.—<hi>Elders.</hi> This Verſion of ours well agrees with the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac;</hi> the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it by <hi>Seniores;</hi> the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> by, <hi>Auncients.</hi> But theſe men render it by <hi>Prétres,</hi> i. e. <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Whereas the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Edition renders to the ſame ſenſe that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> do.</p>
            <p>Act. xvii. 6.—<hi>The world.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>la Ville,</hi> i.e. <hi>the City.</hi> I muſt confeſs that our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have ſome pretence for this Verſion, becauſe the preſent <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it by <hi>urbem.</hi> Nor ſhould I have mentioned this Verſion, had they in other places kept to their Copy, and had there not been great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions that the <hi>Vulgar</hi> did not from the beginning thus turn the <hi>Greek</hi> word? 'tis an eaſie change from <hi>orbem</hi> to <hi>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem,</hi> and 'tis very probable that it ought in this place to be <hi>orbem</hi> in the <hi>Latin</hi> Copy of the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> My reaſons are theſe
<list>
                  <item>[1.] The <hi>Vulgar</hi> never renders the <hi>Greek</hi> word in any other place of the <hi>N.T.</hi> as 'tis ſuppoſed to do here by <hi>urbem,</hi> but conſtantly by <hi>orbem,</hi> as I ſuppoſe it ſhould be here. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it renders this <hi>Greek</hi> word beſides in the <hi>N.T.</hi> it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54146:17"/>to it ſelf. This will appear to any man that will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the <hi>Greek</hi> and the <hi>Vulgar</hi> in the following places, <hi>Matt. xxiv.</hi> 14. <hi>Luk. ii.</hi> 1. <hi>iv.</hi> 5. <hi>xxi.</hi> 26. <hi>Act. xi.</hi> 28. <hi>xvii.</hi> 31. <hi>xix.</hi> 27. <hi>xxiv.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom. x.</hi> 18. <hi>Heb. i.</hi> 6. <hi>ii.</hi> 5. <hi>Apoc. iii.</hi> 10. <hi>xii.</hi> 9. Theſe, with this, <hi>Act. xvii.</hi> 6. are all the places in which this <hi>Greek</hi> word is found and tranſlated by the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly (excepting this one place, <hi>Acts xvii.</hi> 6.) turn'd agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to <hi>orbem</hi> which I contend for here. Indeed the <hi>Greek</hi> word is found in our preſent <hi>Greek</hi> Copy, <hi>Apoc. xvi.</hi> 14. But there the word is not turn'd by the <hi>Vulgar</hi> at all. Of which 'tis no hard matter to give an account were it not too great a digreſſion.</item>
                  <item>[2.) This rendring which I contend for is more agreeable to the Context. <hi>Theſe that have turned the world upſide down,</hi> (<hi>&amp; huc venerunt,</hi> V.L.) <hi>are come hither alſo.</hi> 'Twould be nothing to the purpoſe to have ſaid, That they who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd that City were come thither alſo. But very pertinent to warn the Citizens that they had diſturb'd other places before.</item>
                  <item>[3.] Nor do I want authority on my ſide. The <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion give great aſſurance that this is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the place.</item>
               </list> And we may collect ſomething to the ſame purpoſe from the Popiſh Verſions alſo. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> are ſtrict Interpreters of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and yet they render it by <hi>world</hi> (agreeably to <hi>orbem,</hi>) the Tranſlation of <hi>Mons</hi> by <hi>toute la Terre,</hi> i.e. <hi>all the Earth</hi> (as 'tis in the <hi>Syriac</hi> Verſion:) the old <hi>Louvain</hi> tranſlation hath <hi>le monde,</hi> i.e. <hi>the world.</hi> 'Tis true indeed that <hi>Amelote</hi> (in his firſt Edition at <hi>Paris, A.D.</hi> 1666.) renders it, <hi>la ville,</hi> as our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines do. But then it is as true, that the ſame man (in his Edition at <hi>Paris, A.D.</hi> 1686.) hath rendred it by, <hi>toute la terre,</hi> i.e. <hi>all the earth,</hi> and hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his former Verſion in the remaining words of the verſe alſo, which does much confirm what I contend for. For whereas in his former Edition, he turns thoſe words, <hi>are come hither alſo,</hi> by, <hi>&amp; qui ſont venus icy,</hi> i.e. <hi>and who are come hither:</hi> In his latter Edition he turns them thus, <hi>&amp; qui ſont venus ici pour le meſme effet,</hi> i.e. <hi>and who are come hither for the ſame purpoſe.</hi> I may add to what hath been ſaid, that it is certain
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54146:17"/>that ſeveral Copies of the <hi>V. Latin</hi> have <hi>orbem</hi> in the Text. We have two printed by <hi>Plantin</hi> (before the Copy of <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. which is now follow'd) one of the N. Teſtament by the Divines of <hi>Louvain, A.D.</hi> 1574. Another of the whole Bible printed by him alſo, <hi>A.D.</hi> 1582. and that by the care of the Divines of <hi>Louvain</hi> alſo. In both theſe we find <hi>orbem</hi> in the Text, and whoever under ſtands the care of thoſe men cannot ſuſpect their integrity in this matter. Moreover in the <hi>French</hi> Bible, printed by the order of <hi>Charles</hi> V. viewed by the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, and printed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly at <hi>Antwerp, A.D.</hi> 1534. 'tis from the <hi>Vulgar</hi> rendred <hi>le monde,</hi> i.e. <hi>the world,</hi> as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> hath it.</p>
            <p>Act. xvii. 9. <hi>Security.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Pexcuſe,</hi> i.e. <hi>excuſe.</hi> It is very plain that this is no true rendring of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which renders it by <hi>ſatisfactione,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſatisfaction:</hi> The <hi>Mons</hi> renders it by <hi>Caution,</hi> the old <hi>Louvain</hi> by <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> agreeably to the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Verſion and the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Teſtament of <hi>Rhemes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—ver. 30. <hi>Winked at.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Ayant pitie,</hi> i.e. <hi>having pity.</hi> This is an extravagant tranſlation: for the <hi>Vulgar</hi> renders it by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciens:</hi> and the other Popiſh Verſions are very far from agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this Verſion.</p>
            <p>Act. xxvii. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. V.L. <hi>cum ſuſtuliſſent de Aſſon.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>ayant lovè l' Anchre d' Aſſon.</hi> Theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have added to the Text without giving notice to the Reader by a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent character. 'Tis true that the <hi>Vulgar</hi> ſeems to underſtand <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to be the name of a place, and therefore 'tis no wonder this Verſion ſhould follow that. And tho' it do not appear that it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie any place, yet I cannot blame theſe men for following their Copy. But this will not excuſe their addition. I paſs by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſe, becauſe therein theſe Interpreters follow the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</hi> And ſo they do <hi>ch.</hi> xxviii. 11. Where what we render, <hi>Caſtor and Pollux,</hi> they render by <hi>Caſtors.</hi> Tho' the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion, <hi>Amelote</hi> and that of <hi>Mons</hi> agree with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. ii. 13. <hi>Comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual.</hi> V.L. <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus ſpiritualia comparantes.</hi> Here's a perfect agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>V. Latin.</hi> The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> turn it, <hi>comparing ſpiritual things to the ſpiritual.</hi> But our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines render it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54146:18"/>by, <hi>approprians les choſes ſpirituelles à ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> quiſont ſpirituels,</hi> i.e. <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating ſpiritual things to ſpiritual perſons.</hi> I leave it to any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different perſon to judge which of theſe Verſions beſt agrees with the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> The caſe is plain, that we have rendred <hi>comparantes</hi> in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> better than they have done, who are not agreeable to the Text of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and render it very differently from <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lote,</hi> and the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſtament.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. viii. 4. <hi>And that there is none other God but one.</hi> V. L. <hi>Fr quod nullus eſt Deus niſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us.</hi> Whoever conſiders the <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riac,</hi> the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and the Context, cannot doubt of the truth of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion of this place. But beſides all this, 'tis farther juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the moſt celebrated Verſions of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> that are in vogue with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion agrees exactly with ours. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> turn to the ſame ſenſe, and ſo does <hi>Amelote,</hi> and the Authors of the tranſlation of <hi>Mons.</hi> But theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines turn the words to another ſenſe againſt all the reaſon of the thing, the Authority of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and of the other Popiſh Verſions: For thus they turn theſe words, <hi>Et qu'il n'y a aucun Dieu,</hi> i.e. <hi>And that there is no God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Cor. ix. 3. <hi>Examine.</hi> V. L. <hi>Interrogant.</hi> Our rendring agrees with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and with the <hi>Rhemiſts:</hi> The old <hi>Louvain</hi> renders it by <hi>Examinent;</hi> but thoſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines by <hi>Contróllent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phil. ii. 11. <hi>And that every tongue ſhould confeſs, that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord to the glory of God the father.</hi> V. L. <hi>&amp; omnis lingua conſiteatur, quia Dominus J. Chriſtus in gloria eſt Dei Patris.</hi> Thus theſe words are rendred by our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, <hi>&amp; que toute langue confeſſe que le Seigneur J. Chriſt eſt en la gloire de Dieu le Pere,</hi> i.e. <hi>and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tongue confeſs that the Lord J. Chriſt is in the glory of God the father.</hi> The words of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> as they are diſtinguiſhed in the ordinary Copy, do not infer the ſenſe which this Verſion gives them. For the Confeſſion may well belong to what goes before; and then the ground of it follows, <hi>quia Dominus Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi> But I lay no great ſtreſs upon this reflection.</p>
            <p>Heb. xi. 3. <hi>Of.</hi> V. L. <hi>Ex.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Par,</hi> i. e. <hi>by;</hi> which quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the ſenſe of the place, and by no means agrees with the <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> which theſe men pretend to tranſlate.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54146:18"/>
            <p>I ſhall next obſerve ſome groſs omiſſions in this tranſlation of theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines. I ſhall paſs by thoſe of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and only mention ſuch omiſſions as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> will not warrant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom. xii.</hi> 9. Cleave to that which is <hi>good.</hi> The word <hi>good</hi> is in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but is left out of the Text by theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines.</p>
            <p>Rom. xv. 3. <hi>Of them that reproached thee.</hi> Theſe words are in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but are omitted by theſe Tranſlators.</p>
            <p>Rev. i. 4. <hi>Seven.</hi> This is in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but omitted in our <hi>French</hi> tranſlation.</p>
            <p>Joh. vii. 22. <hi>Therefore.</hi> V.L. <hi>Propterea.</hi> This is omitted by this Tranſlation, both in the 21, and 22. verſes: For 'tis a queſtion to which the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> belongs.</p>
            <p>2 Cor. iv. 2. <hi>Commending our ſelves to every mans Conſcience.</hi> Thus 'tis alſo in the <hi>V. Latin.</hi> But this tranſlation leaves out what is in the <hi>Latin,</hi> tho' it quite ſpoil the ſenſe of the place: Thus 'tis ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred by theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, <hi>nous approuvans toute conſcience, &amp;c.</hi> i.e. <hi>we approving every conſcience of men.</hi> In the very next verſe, if <hi>our Goſpel be hid:</hi> The <hi>French</hi> tranſlation leaves out the word, <hi>hid,</hi> tho' it be in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and the ſenſe of the place be imperfect without it.</p>
            <p>2 Cor. vii. 2. What <hi>clearing of your ſelves.</hi> This is omitted by theſe <hi>Louvain Divines.</hi> But 'tis rendred by <hi>defenſionem</hi> in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and by <hi>defence</hi> in the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion.</p>
            <p>Eph. iv. 31. <hi>With all malice.</hi> V. L. <hi>cum omni malitià.</hi> Theſe words are alſo left out by our Divines of <hi>Louvain.</hi> But the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines have theſe words.</p>
            <p>Col. ii. 14. <hi>Which was contrary to us.</hi> The <hi>Vulgar</hi> reads thus: and the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> have it ſo, and the old <hi>Louvain</hi> agrees with them, yet our new <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines omit theſe words.</p>
            <p>1 Theſſ. i. 1. <hi>Grace.</hi> This is in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and the old <hi>Louvain,</hi> tho' omitted in this Verſion.</p>
            <p>Heb. viii. 12. They omit <hi>for,</hi> tho' it be in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and <hi>ch.</hi> xii. 27. <hi>Things that are ſhaken,</hi> which the <hi>Vulgar</hi> expreſſeth by <hi>mobilium,</hi> is omitted in this tranſlation.</p>
            <p>1 Joh. ii. 1. <hi>Righteous.</hi> The <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> hath it. So hath the old <hi>Louvain:</hi> Theſe Tranſlators omit it, tho' it cannot be ſpared,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54146:19"/>Again, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. Theſe Tranſlators leave out the particle <hi>and.</hi> And then their tranſlation amounts to thus much. <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light hateth his brother, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other omiſſions are not to be charged upon our Divines of <hi>Louvain,</hi> becauſe they are ſuch as are warranted by the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which they pretend to tranſlate. Theſe are ſuch as follow, <hi>Matt. vi.</hi> 4, 6, 13, 18. <hi>Luk. xi.</hi> 2. <hi>Joh. x.</hi> 42. <hi>Act. xxiii.</hi> 9. 1 <hi>Tim. iv.</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Pet. i.</hi> 7. <hi>Rev. i.</hi> 10. <hi>ch. ii.</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now reflect upon the <hi>Additions</hi> which theſe <hi>Lou.</hi> Divines have made to the Text, and ſuch as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> will not warrant. Some of theſe I have upon occaſion nam'd already; the reſt follow.</p>
            <p>Rom. iii. 10. <hi>No not one.</hi> The <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines add to theſe words out of their own heads, <hi>devant la foy,</hi> i.e. <hi>before the Faith.</hi> The <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath no ſuch thing; nor the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. vi. 13. <hi>The Lord of the body.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>le Seigneur pourvoira all corps.</hi> Here they add to the Text, which the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and old <hi>Louvain</hi> do not.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. ix. 5. <hi>Have we not power to lead about a ſiſter, a wife:</hi> Theſe <hi>Lou.</hi> Divines add, <hi>pour nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervir en l' Evangile, &amp; nous ſouvenir de ſes biens,</hi> i.e. <hi>To ſerve us in the Goſpel, and relieve us out of her goods.</hi> In the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and old <hi>Louvain</hi> there is nothing to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. xi. 26, 27, 28. <hi>Bread.</hi> There is no Epithete in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> in any of theſe places, nor in the old <hi>Louvain,</hi> But theſe men render it <hi>ver.</hi> 26. by <hi>pain vivant,</hi> i.e. <hi>living bread; ver.</hi> 27. by <hi>pain de vie,</hi> i.e. <hi>bread of life;</hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 28. by <hi>pain vif.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Cor. i. 12. <hi>For our rejoicing is this.</hi> Theſe men add, <hi>à ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avoir le tes moinage de notre gloire,</hi> i. e. viz. <hi>the teſtimony of our glory.</hi> There's nothing of this in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> or old <hi>Louvain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gal. iv. 3. <hi>Elements of the world.</hi> Theſe men add, <hi>ſous la loy;</hi> the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it not, nor the old <hi>Louvain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Theſſ. iv. 13. <hi>That ſleep in Jeſus.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>qui dorment du ſommeil de paix en Jeſus.</hi> The old <hi>Louvain</hi> and <hi>Vulgar</hi> will not warrant this addition.</p>
            <p>Heb. v. 7.—<hi>was heard, in that he feared.</hi> Theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines add theſe words, <hi>quand il a eſtè reſuſcitè.</hi> i.e. <hi>when he was raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi> But there is no ſuch thing either in the old <hi>Louvain,</hi> or <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:54146:19"/>
            <p>Heb. viii. 2, 6. <hi>To miniſter. ver.</hi> 2. (which our Interpreters render by <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourge,</hi> in which they do not follow the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>) they add the word <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficattur.</hi> And to the word <hi>miniſtery, ver.</hi> 6. (which they render by <hi>Litourgie,</hi> rejecting the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Verſion) they add, <hi>Sacrificature.</hi> And yet the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> and old <hi>Louvain</hi> give them no occaſion for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Heb. x 9, 18. To theſe words, <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>He taketh away the firſt,</hi> our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators make bold to add to the Text the word <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> And <hi>v</hi> 18. to thoſe words, <hi>there is no more offering,</hi> they add <hi>Legale,</hi> i. e. ſuch as the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> required. There's nothing in the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> or old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion will juſtifie theſe additions. But theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines make no ſcruple to add theſe words that they may ſupport the <hi>Romiſh</hi> doctrine of the Sacrifice of the Maſs. Theſe are ſoul arts indeed, and they have no reaſon to pretend, not ſhadow of authority for their excuſe.</p>
            <p>1 Pet. iii. 15. <hi>Of the hope.</hi> Theſe men add, <hi>&amp; de la foy.</hi> But there is no ſuch thing in the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Pet. v. 3. <hi>Over</hi> God's <hi>heritage.</hi> In the Greek, 'tis only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> renders it, <hi>in cleris,</hi> keeping to the Greek word; ſo far is the <hi>Vulgar</hi> from determining the ſenſe to perſons onthings, much leſs to particular perſons or a ſeparate order of men. But our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines are not ſcrupulous and nice in this matter. They have it thus, <hi>ſur le Clerge. ou ſur les heritages du Seigneur.</hi> i.e. <hi>over the Clergy, or over the heritages of the Lord?</hi> 'Tis not agreed yet, that by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text is meant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and if it were, 'tis not certain that the Clergy excluſively to the reſt of God's people are meant. Be all this as it will, theſe men have not done ſincerely, nor as becomes ſtrict Interpreters, not having kept to the <hi>Vulgar</hi> which they pretend to tranſlate. Father <hi>Amelote</hi> in his notes upon this place does obſerve, that <hi>in Cleris,</hi> in the <hi>Vulgar</hi> here, does not ſignifie <hi>dans le Clergé.</hi> And therefore he does not render it thus: nor do the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the <hi>Mons</hi> tranſlation expound <hi>heritage</hi> by <hi>Clergy</hi> in the Text of their Verſion: but render the word as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> doth.</p>
            <p>2 Pet. iii. 17. <hi>Error of the wicked.</hi> In the <hi>Vulgar</hi> it is, <hi>Inſipientium er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore,</hi> i. e. <hi>the error of the fooliſh.</hi> This is by our <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by, <hi>erreur des mechans heretiques,</hi> i. e. <hi>the error of wicked hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 John ii. 14. <hi>The wicked one.</hi> Theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Tranſlators without any regard to their Copy, the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> or their Predeceſſors, the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines; have out of their own heads, added to the Text, <hi>&amp; ſes mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres,</hi> i.e. <hi>and his Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rev. xviii. 20. <hi>Holy Apoſtles.</hi> This agrees with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and with the old Verſion of the <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines; but theſe new Divines will render it, <hi>Saints, Apoſtres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are indeed in this Tranſlation, a very great number of additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Text, if by the Text we underſtand the preſent <hi>Greek.</hi> But
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54146:20"/>theſe <hi>Louvain:</hi> Divines are not to be charged with them, becauſe they are found in the <hi>Vulgar.</hi> The Reader that is curious may find ſome of them in the following places, <hi>Matt. xxv.</hi> 1. <hi>Act. xviii.</hi> 7. <hi>xxiii.</hi> 25. <hi>Rom. iv.</hi> 5. <hi>viii.</hi> 28. 1 <hi>Cor. xii.</hi> 28. <hi>xvi.</hi> 19. 2 <hi>Cor. i.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Phil. iv.</hi> 8. 1 <hi>Pet. v.</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Joh. ii.</hi> 14. <hi>Rev. ix.</hi> 11. <hi>xviii.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>I might add to what hath been ſaid, very fitly in this place, that theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, inſtead of giving the Reader a ſtrict Verſion of the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> do impoſe upon him a ſenſe of their own, and take the liberty of a <hi>Paraphraſt</hi> inſtend of keeping to the ſtrict rules of a good Interpreter.</p>
            <p>Thus they do (1 <hi>Cor. xi.</hi> 10.) as I have remarked upon another occaſion. And <hi>ch. xvi.</hi> 9. Where we read a <hi>great door and effectual:</hi> And the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> hath it, <hi>oſtium magnum &amp; evidens:</hi> theſe men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender it by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grande &amp; favourable occaſion.</hi> This is a liberty which the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines would not take. They truly render the <hi>Vulgar</hi> by <hi>une grande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> evidente porte.</hi> I do not contend about the ſenſe of the place: But theſe men ought not to give a <hi>Comment</hi> when they undertake a <hi>Verſion</hi> only And tho they thought fit thus to turn the place, they ought to have added ſome Marginal note or remark for the Readers uſe. Thus, <hi>Coleſſ. ii.</hi> 20. <hi>Living in the world.</hi> Theſe men add to the very Text, <hi>&amp; deſſous la Loy,</hi> by way of explication, when there is no ſuch thing in the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> nor in the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Edition. <hi>Amelote</hi> takes not this liberty, and the Authors of the <hi>Mons</hi> make a diſtinction of character between the Text and their Supplements: <hi>ver.</hi> 22. they take the ſame liberty, where, after the word <hi>uſing</hi> they add, <hi>eſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> eſtablies,</hi> i.e. <hi>being eſtabliſhed;</hi> And yet the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and old <hi>Louvain</hi> Edition hath nothing like it. Again, <hi>Heb. ix.</hi> 22. We read it, <hi>without ſhedding of bloud is no remiſſion.</hi> Both the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion agree exactly with ours. Theſe men render it thus, <hi>ſans effuſion de ſang des b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es la ſouilleure legalen'eſt point oſtée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> i.e. <hi>without the effuſion of the bloud of beaſts legul impurity is not taken away.</hi> There are ſeveral other ſuch places as theſe where theſe men add to the Text of the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> viz. 1 <hi>Pet. i.</hi> 4. 2 <hi>Pet. i.</hi> 14. &amp; <hi>ch. ii.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed in many partic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lars how inconſiſtent this Verſion is with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> which it pretends to tranſlate, and that of the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, whoſe it pretends to be. I ſhall now ſhew how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent it is with it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Matt. iv. 10. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> This place is perfectly parallel to <hi>Luke. iv.</hi> 8. There can be no pretence for any difference in the Verſion. And yet theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines are herein inconſiſtent with themſelves; for they give a Verſion of one place different from what they had given of the ſame words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as hath been obſerved elſewhere upon another occaſion. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Matt. xv.</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 5. and <hi>Mark vii.</hi> 11. where (without
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54146:20"/>the authority of the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi>) thoſe men give us a different ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of the ſame words, tho' they are parallel places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act. xi.</hi> 30. What we render <hi>Elders,</hi> they render by <hi>Pretres,</hi> i.e. <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and yet the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it <hi>Seniores.</hi> This they do alſo, <hi>Act. xv.</hi> 22. and <hi>ch. xxi.</hi> 18. where the <hi>Vulgar</hi> hath it as before. This is not to follow their Copy; nor do they conſiſt with themſelves. For in other places they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame word by <hi>Anciens, Matt. xxvii.</hi> 1, 3, 12. And by <hi>Vieillard,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim. v.</hi> 1. So that they do not follow the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> nor agree with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They depart from it frequently, and follow it where there is leaſt reaſon. And inſtance of which we have, and a notorious one in <hi>Act. xx.</hi> 17. <hi>The Elders of the Church,</hi> one might have expected they ſhould have tranſlated by <hi>Prieſts of the Church,</hi> conſidering how ſond they are of tranſlating the word <hi>Elders</hi> by <hi>Prieſts</hi> in other places: no wonder they ſhould tranſlate <hi>Elders</hi> by <hi>Anciens, Matt. xxvii.</hi> 1. becauſe they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid to be <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> and conſequently to be reckoned among the Laity. But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d called Elders of the Church. And theſe very Tranſlators, <hi>ch. xiv.</hi> 43. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>They ordained Elders in every Church,</hi> tranſlate the word <hi>Elders</hi> by <hi>Pretres,</hi> i.e. <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Yet in this place they tranſlate <hi>Elders of the Church</hi> by, <hi>les plus ages de l'Egliſe:</hi> i.e. <hi>the more aged of the Church.</hi> The <hi>V. Latin</hi> hath it indeed, <hi>majores natu Eccleſia:</hi> But the Context aſſures us they were <hi>Eccleſiaſtics.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Antelote</hi> renders it by <hi>Preſtres,</hi> i.e. <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſo does the <hi>Mons</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo, and theſe men might have done it here with more ſhew of reaſon than elſewhere. But they who regard not the <hi>Vulgar</hi> elſewhere are tenacious of it where there is no cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act. xxvi.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Fr. Tr. <hi>Commanca a rendre raiſon,</hi> i.e. <hi>began to render a reaſon.</hi> I do not quarrel about their rendring, becauſe herein theſe men follow the <hi>Vulgar Latin.</hi> I only ſhew that they do not the part of good Interpreters in that they are not conſonant to themſelves: For <hi>ver.</hi> 24. where there is the ſame word in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the ſame rendring in the <hi>V. Latin,</hi> and the very ſame ſubject matter, yet they alter their phraſe: There they render <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by, <hi>comme il ſe defendoit;</hi> which is an argument of great levity in Interpreters; and eſpecially in them who pretend to be the <hi>Louvain</hi> Interpreters; whereas the old <hi>Louvain</hi> tranſlation is in both places conformable to the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> and conſonant to itſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act. xxvi.</hi> 24, 25. In the ſame Chapter we find as great a Blunder as that mentioned above. <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Paul Mairy,</hi> i.e. <hi>Thou art mad.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Vous perdez le ſenſe,</hi> i.e. <hi>You have loſt your wits.</hi> I diſpute not the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, but truly repreſent the folly and levity of the tranſlators. For whereas the <hi>Greek</hi> word is the ſame, the <hi>Vulgar</hi> Verſion the ſame, the ſubject matter the very ſames yet theſe Interpreters have uſed three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54146:21"/>ways of rendring the ſame <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> word. The firſt as is ſaid, they render by, <hi>vous pardez le ſenſe:</hi> The ſecond by <hi>fou,</hi> i.e. <hi>a fool:</hi> The third by, <hi>inſensè,</hi> i.e. <hi>one that hath not his ſenſe.</hi> In this they did not follow the old <hi>Louvain</hi> Verſion, the Authors of that took greater care.</p>
            <p>1 Cor. x. 14. <hi>Flee from Idolatry.</hi> Fr. Tr. <hi>Fuyez l'adoration des idoles,</hi> i.e. <hi>flee the adoration of Idols.</hi> I do not here charge theſe men with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from their Copy, the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> in this place. That which they are blameable for, is that in another place, where there is not only the ſame <hi>Greek</hi> word, but the <hi>Vulgar</hi> tranſlates it to the ſame ſenſe as it does here, theſe <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines, as inconſiſtent both with the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and themſelves, render it by <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as may be ſeen by conſulting their Verſion of <hi>Galat. v.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor. xvi.</hi> 9. with 2 <hi>Cor. ii.</hi> 12. Whereas in one of theſe places they render <hi>door</hi> by <hi>occaſion</hi> (as I have obſerved before on another occaſion) theſe new <hi>Louvain</hi> Divines forget themſelves when they come to the latter of the abovenamed places. And tho' the <hi>Vulgar</hi> uſe the ſame word, <hi>oſtium,</hi> in both places, and the ſubject matter be one and the ſame, yet what they render by, <hi>occaſion,</hi> in one place, in the other they render by, <hi>la porte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with repreſenting to the Reader ſome <hi>Errata</hi> of the Preſs. Theſe indeed are the leaſt faults, but yet not to be excuſed in a work of this nature. Thoſe to whom this care belonged ought to have prevented theſe <hi>Errata,</hi> or to have given the Reader ſome notice of them, whereas they have done neither of them.</p>
            <p>Matt. xxvii. 7. This Verſion hath <hi>Haſeldama,</hi> where the <hi>V. Latin</hi> hath <hi>Haceldama;</hi> and the old <hi>Louvain, Acheldemach.</hi> Luk. i. 27. This Verſion hath <hi>Anne,</hi> for <hi>Aune,</hi> as the old <hi>Louvain</hi> hath it. Luk. iii. 1. <hi>Ceſa,</hi> for <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi> Joh. ix. 2. <hi>Sa</hi> inſtead of <hi>ſa m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</hi> Act. xii. 2. where the following words are repeated <hi>voulant le produire apres Pâques.</hi> 1 Cor. vii. 9. <hi>Li</hi> for <hi>il.</hi> ch. ix. 15. <hi>Nom</hi> for <hi>Mon.</hi> ch. xv. 29. <hi>notal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment</hi> for <hi>Totalement,</hi> as it is in the old <hi>Louvain,</hi> Gal. ii. 9. <hi>Centils</hi> for <hi>Centil's,</hi> as 'tis in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> Coloſſ. ii. 13. <hi>Enſembe</hi> for <hi>Enſemble,</hi> is 'tis in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> 2 Theſſ. iii. 6. <hi>Tradiction</hi> for <hi>Tradition,</hi> as in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> Heb. xii. 26. <hi>Mes</hi> for <hi>Mais.</hi> ch. x. 30. <hi>pleuple</hi> for <hi>peuple.</hi> Jam. i. 1. <hi>tribus</hi> for <hi>Tribus.</hi> 1 Joh. i. 1, 3. <hi>ven ouy</hi> for <hi>ven &amp; ouy,</hi> as 'tis in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> Rev. vi. 16. <hi>Tone</hi> for <hi>Throne.</hi> ch. vii. 4. <hi>Tributs</hi> for <hi>Tribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> xi. 18. <hi>Non</hi> for <hi>Nom,</hi> as it is in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> ch xvii. 17. <hi>aeuvres</hi> for <hi>coeurs,</hi> as 'tis in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> ch. xx. 5. <hi>Teſtes,</hi> for <hi>reſte,</hi> as in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi> ch. xxii. 2. <hi>Sanctè</hi> for <hi>Santè,</hi> as 'tis in the old <hi>Louvain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54146:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
